Hi, this is the
question review
for congestive
heart failure.
A 79-year-old male
with the history of
CHF was brought to
the ED with dyspnea
and a heart rate of
100 beats per minute.
An echo revealed a
worsening in its left
ventricular function
and the physician
decided on treatment
with milrinone.
What's the
mechanism? So we
know that there
are certain drugs
like milrinone,
dobutamine,
digoxin, which will
in fact enhance
contractility. They're
positive inotropic
in nature. They're
going to increase
calcium in to enhance
contractility.
And they don't
do so via various
mechanisms. So, for
example, the first one,
blockade of sodium
-potassium ATPase,
that will, in
fact, now affect
the sodium-calcium
exchange mechanism.
Where sodium is
now in the cell,
calcium doesn't get
pumped out, and that
leads to positive
inotropic effects.
And that's going to
be true of digoxin.
So the doxin is not
the best answer here
because we're looking
for milrinone.
Direct activation
of beta-1 receptors,
that's a G
-stimulatory mechanism,
and that is achieved
by dobutamine. And by
increasing CAMP and
then increasing protein
kinase A, which is
what we want, you
would get calcium in
for the contractility.
But this does
so directly.
Donation of nitric
oxide will reduce
preload, and that's
going to be true of, say,
nitroprusside
or isosorbide
or nitroglycerin.
That is not the
mechanism of milrinone.
Milrinone will
enhance cyclic AMP by
inhibiting this enzyme.
So if this stays
elevated, you're
going to increase
protein kinase A, and
that leads to enhanced
contractility.
That's an indirect.
So D is the best answer.
And then enhanced
cyclic GMP by blocking
PDE5 is true for
the ED drugs like
sildenafil. So by doing
that, you're going
to get smooth muscle
relaxation and that
will improve blood
flow to that area.
If you gave a nitric
oxide donor with
one of these, you're
going to super
increase this. and
that's going to lead
to excessive smooth
muscle relaxation.
That can lead to
hypotension and that will
invoke, by baroreceptor
reflex mechanisms,
reflexive tachycardia.
And then ACE,
which is the prills
that group the RAS
drugs are used mainly
for chronic heart
failure. so D is in fact
the best answer that
is the mechanism of
action of milrinone
and again if we want
to do the nitty gritty
here we understand
that milrinone will
block this to increase
cyclic AMP to increase
protein kinase A
dobutamine binds here
G-stimulatory is
true of all the beta
receptors, and that too
will increase cyclic
AMP and increase
protein kinase A through
this mechanism to
raise contractility.
Remember that these drugs
are not used every day.
They're used
mainly for acute
decompensated congestive
heart failure.
Dobutamine can be
sometimes used for shock
cases mainly when
we're talking about
a lowering of cardiac
output we worry
about invoking
sympathetics and that is
blocked by the beta
blockers and we're also
going to get an
increase in RAS which is
managed by giving
any of the RAS drugs
The Prils, the
Sartans, the Arnie, and
the mineral corticoid
receptor blockers.
This patient had
hypertension.
He started on medication.
The blood pressure
got better,
but he presented
with this effect.
What caused this
presentation?
So this is a swelling
of the tongue.
It could be swelling
of the lips,
the throat,
the GI tract. And that
is due to bradykinin.
Bradykinin releases
these pro-inflammatory
mediators to cause
this. It can also cause
bronchoconstriction
that will cause a cough.
And that's due to the
fact that you don't
have ACE present to
break down bradykinin.
So this is
angioedema. You're
looking at the choices.
D would be the
best answer. If you
wanted to preserve
this mechanism and not
have an effect on
ACE or bradykinin,
you would give
an angiotensin
1 blocker like
the sartans.
Beta 1 blockers, if
anything, I would
be concerned with
AB node blockade.
So watch the
patient's heart rate.
Calcium channel
blockers like diltiazem
and verapamil work in
the SA and AV node.
They too can produce
AV node block.
Increased cyclic GMP
production, that's going
to be true of something
like hydralazine.
And remember, hydralazine
is also acetylated.
And that's
another drug like
procainamide that we
studied before that
can cause the drug
-induced lupus.
This is the best answer.
These are the prills.
And then inhibition
of the sodium
chloride co
-transporter is going
to be used for
managing edema.
And edema, again, is
managed with diuretics.
Diuretics help
with the symptoms,
but unlike the other
drugs like the RAS
drugs or the beta
blockers, they don't,
as of now, prolong
survival with CHF. If
you start a RAS drug,
remember, they're
going to reduce preload
and afterload. So
there's vasodilation
attached to them.
You would have to
tell the patient in
the first few doses
to rise slowly. Or if
you're raising their
dose, you have to
be mindful because if
they rise too slowly,
they could end up
dizzy and falling.
What's common to
all the RAS drugs,
including alaskirin,
is the fact
that they will
block aldosterone.
Blocking aldosterone
is a good thing.
It gets rid of
the sodium in the
water, but it
recovers potassium.
So that's going to
be common to all of
these drugs, including
the mineral corticoid
receptor antagonists
like Spirano.
Drug interactions,
anything that has a
hyperkalemic effect,
you need to monitor.
Renal artery
stenosis. So if you're
blocking angio-2
in these patients,
that patient
is not going to
have anything to
maintain their GFR.
So that's a
contraindication.
On the flip side,
if you have a
diabetic and your
concerns with
nephropathy, you do
want to lower GFR.
Because if the GFR is
high, you're going to
get a lot of protein
spilling into the urine.
So because of that
mechanism, that's
actually a benefit for
type 2 diabetics when
we want to preserve
their renal function. And
I'll go through that
next semester again.
Contraindicated in
pregnancy, and the
reason being is
that they affect the
formation of the renal
system in the fetus.
So if you need
something for pregnancy,
you should do methyl
dopa or libetolol.
this 56 year old
presented to the physician
after being
diagnosed with CHF
after an MI his blood
pressure is elevated
and he is having
edema in his ankles
he's not able to
breathe well at
night and they start
him on a sodium
and water or
decreaser, so it's
got to be some
type of diuretic.
At the next visit,
he improves,
but he also tells
the physician
that he has got
an enlarged chest.
If this is a result of
a specific diuretic,
where in the nephron
does it work? So
this is a very important
question because
USMLE especially
doesn't always ask
straightforward
mechanism. they may say,
where in the nephron
does this drug
work? So this is
implying to me that there
is some anti-androgen
effects here.
And that is going
to be true with
the mineral
corticoid receptor
blocker known as
spironolactone.
And that effect is a
benefit in dermatology,
where if you give this
medication you will
have now a decrease
in hair growth and
that's known as hirsutism
is excessive hair
growth and you'll
also get a decrease in
hormonal acne because
of the anti-androgen
effects. However, in
some patients, especially
if we're talking about
males, you may get
an increase in breast
mass or chest mass.
And you may also get
some degree of impotence.
So, aldosterone
is going to be
specific to the
collecting duct.
And that's going to
be the correct answer.
The DCT is the
site of the
sodium chloride
co-transporter.
And by blocking there,
you're going to get
rid of sodium, water,
potassium, hydrogen ion,
but you're going to
recover your calcium.
Glomerulus, no site of
drug action
at the moment.
Loop of Henle is
going to be the
sodium, potassium,
and 2-chloride.
These are considered
to be high
ceiling. They get
rid of everything,
including magnesium,
including calcium.
And that has to do
with a decrease in
PTH, which reduces
calcium recovery.
With the DCT drugs,
there's actually an
enhancement of
the PTH, and that
recovers calcium from
the collecting duct.
the loops also
cause ototoxicity
and the loops and
the thiazides have a
sulfonamide group the
only one that doesn't
of the group is going
to be ethacrinic
acid and as I mentioned
in the lecture,
ethacrinic has the
most ototoxicity
and then the PCT is
not the site of action
of any of the diuretics
we use in cardiology
This will cause acidosis,
and for the most
part, we use this in
narrow-angled glaucoma
if we want to, in fact,
stop the production
of aqueous humor that
comes from bicarbonate.
Or we want to make
the urine alkanalized.
Or if the patient is
climbing a mountain
and needs to blow off
that carbon dioxide,
acetazolamide,
which is the main
drug of the
PCT, works here.
Those are carbonic
anhydrase inhibitors.
So aldosterone blockers,
again, in the principal
cells of the kidney,
you're going to block
aldosterone. Get
rid of the sodium in
the water, you're going
to recover potassium
and hydrogen ion,
and that is going to
be known as acidosis.
Acidosis happens
because aldosterone
is blocked and that
impairs hydrogen
ion secretion. And
that happens in
the intercalated
cells of the kidney.
Okay,
again, that's
gynecomastia.
Anything that creates
more hyperkalemia
will be a problem and
you need to watch the
levels of potassium
throughout therapy.
Digoxin, even though we
worry more about
hypokalemia,
digoxin itself, by
inhibiting sodium
-potassium ATPase,
can lead to higher
levels of potassium
in the blood.
This patient is 58
and she has orthopnea,
which means she can't
breathe when lying down
that's where they need
a few pillows she has
nocturnal dyspnea and
she wakes up using
the bathroom in the
night nocturia she has a
heart rate of 180
pulmonary rails and that
third heart sound s3
she was getting medicine
for breast cancer
which are the following
that she received so
this is basically saying
what's the toxicity of
the anti-neoplastic.
Bleomycin and bolsulfan
and to an extent
amiodarone from the
last lecture topic will
cause something known
as pulmonary fibrosis.
Cisplatin is an
alkylating agent that has
a platinum group.
Anything that's metallic
is usually hard for
the kidney to excrete
and you're going to
have a high degree of
nephro with cisplatin.
Also Odo and Noro.
Cyclophosphamide
is a pro-drug.
It's going to
be activated.
The alkyl group is
going to bind to N7
of guanine and break
the DNA. But acrayoline
is going to bind
to the bladder to
cause hemorrhagic
cystitis. And you will
give enough hydration
and probably mesna.
Mesna is sulfonated,
binds the
acrayoline and allows
it to be excreted.
Doxyrubicin is red.
This is the one that's
the interculating
agent. It makes
free radicals, which
can damage the
DNA of the cancer
cell, but it also
damages contractile
proteins. And that
is going to cause
something called
dilated cardiomyopathy.
The other drug that
I wanted to mention
is the HER2 drug
for HER2 breast
cancer, and that's
trastuzumab. This
too can also be
hard on the heart.
So if you're using
doxy or trastuzumab,
you're going
to be told that
you need to get
periodic echocardiograms
to check the
left ventricle.
Vincristine microtubules,
this one can
cause something called
pins and needles.
The patient is going
to have in their feet
and hands almost like
a feeling of falling
asleep okay that's a
paresthesia so the best
answer here is going to
be doxorubicin that's
going to cause dilated
cardiomyopathy so
with chf again it
can be caused through
different reasons
maybe uncontrolled
hypertension previous
ischemia arrhythmias.
The glitazones are
going to enhance
ENAC, epithelial
sodium channels in the
collecting duct. If
you're recovering
more sodium and water,
what might happen
is that you're
going to get edema
and that can worsen
somebody with CHF.
NSAIDs, because
they're going to cause
vasoconstriction in
the affron arteriole,
and that's going to
cause now the idea
where you're going to
get, you know, increases,
first of all, in
potassium and a
reduction of both renal
blood flow and GFR.
And cardiac remodeling
is not a good word.
That means the pumping
efficacy has changed.
the muscle is being
mostly replaced by
fibrin and collagen.
And that will enhance
now the idea of that
the heart is not going
to be able to pump as
well, and that's going
to lower your cardiac
output. So the drugs
that are very important
for preventing
cardiac remodeling, a
lot of the RAS drugs.
And to an extent, even
the beta blockers.
this patient is 57 he
presents with crackles
in his lower lung
fields and he also has
petal edema potassium
is high and now they're
saying what would
correct the patient's
electrolyte abnormality
and fluid overload
so there's a couple of
ways to do it there's
potassium binders i I
believe you can give
insulin because that
will now shuttle the
potassium in. But for
this question, we're
really saying, which
drug should he not get?
Blockade of AT1,
that's going
to be an ARB.
And due to the fact that
aldosterone is blocked,
yes, you're getting rid
of sodium and water,
but you're going to
enhance potassium.
This would be worsened.
Blockade of epithelial
sodium channels.
So this is the
opposite of what I just
mentioned with the
thiazolidynidones.
If you're blocking
these channels,
you're going to get
sodium and water out,
but you're going
to raise potassium.
Direct inhibition of
renin, that's going
to stop the conversion
of angiotensinogen
to angio-1. If you
block that with
alaskirin, the renin
blocker, you're still
going to get an
increase in potassium.
With ACE inhibitors, the
story still holds true.
You block aldosterone
and you're raising
potassium levels.
So the last one
makes the most sense
because this drug
class work in the
thick ascending loop
of Henle. They get
rid of everything.
Magnesium, calcium,
water, and potassium.
You're going to
get hypokalemia and
you're also going
to get alkalosis.
And here it's
the opposite.
When you are fluid
depleted, the
body responds by
increasing RAS.
And what is on board
with RAS is aldosterone.
When you raise
aldosterone, then you
get rid of your
potassium and your
hydrogen ion. so
here E is the best
answer that is a
loop diuretic this
will cause a
lowering of potassium
so just a little bit
here with respect
to using these
medications you can use
it for pulmonary edema
hypercalcemia Why?
Because, again,
it's going to be the
opposite of what we
see with thiazides.
Here, there's going
to be a reduction
of parathyroid
hormone, and you're
going to reduce your
calcium recovery.
Again, as I mentioned,
you're going to get,
with respect to the
ear, as I mentioned
in the lecture,
there may be some
effects on, for example,
the fluids and
the ions in the
ear. So you may get more
ototoxicity with
loop diuretics.
And that's going to
be true, especially
if you're giving
other ototoxic drugs.
So if you were in the
hospital being treated
for, say, an infection
with gentamicin
and they needed
to give you a loop
diuretic, you might expect
that the ototoxicity
may be even more
likely to happen.
Again, with the
digoxin, if you're
giving anything
that's going to
affect the potassium
hypokalemia,
now you're potentiating
the action of
that calcium and sodium
exchanger. There's
going to be more
calcium coming in.
to cause that
inotropic effect. And
you're going to see
at around phase four,
the action potential,
a delayed after
depolarization. A
DAD, we call it.
And the way
we manage that
is by giving magnesium.
Because magnesium
will kind of
shift the calcium
out of the cell.
And that's oftentimes
what we would give
for the other condition
known as torsades.
So this 76-year
-old male complained
of shortness of
breath and fatigue,
especially when
lying down at night.
He needed several pillows
to feel comfortable.
He also noticed
swelling in his
feet. His BP
was 140 over 90.
Respirations were 16.
And he had a
pitting leg edema.
EKG revealed a second
degree AV block
a diagnosis of CHF
is confirmed with
the appropriate
therapy following
which should be avoided
so this is pretty
much saying which
of these drugs is an
AV node suppressant
so there's a couple AV
node suppressants
are the beta blockers
the calcium channel
blockers which are
perapamil and diltiazem
remember the dipenes
are not they don't
affect the heart they're
going to affect the
arterial smooth muscle
the other thing is
adenosine and remember
adenosine is not
widely used it's used
for the PSVT adenosine
is used in that
situation because it
works rather quickly.
It stops the episode
and the patient
has a resolution
of the arrhythmia.
But remember,
adenosine itself can
cause some wheezing.
It can cause
some lowering of
blood pressure.
And the other
AV node block is
digoxin. And remember,
digoxin, even
though in this lecture
we talked about
the positive
inotropic effects,
digoxin is also
negative chronotropic.
And that means that it's
going to lower
the heart rate.
And it does so because it
acts parasympathetically.
It has a vagal
component to it.
So B would be
the best answer.
Captopril, no.
So, if anything,
we would get
cough, angioedema,
hyperkalemia.
Aprellinone is the
one of the mineral
corticoid receptor
antagonists that doesn't
have the anti-androgen
effects. So, you
won't see a chest
*********** with this
medication, or the
other one is finernone.
Hydrolazine is going
to raise cyclic GMP,
and that's going to
lower blood pressure.
And then nitroprusside
is the one that
can be both preload
and afterload.
Hydrolazine is just
afterload because
it works on the
arterial oils.
This one works on
the arterioles, but
it also works on
the venous return.
And remember, with
nitroprusside,
that's the one that
has the cyanide.
So if you can't excrete
this moiety, you
can end up going into
cyanide toxicity.
And remember,
that is now a
problem where in
the mitochondria,
you're getting an
inhibition of cytochrome
C oxidase. So
you're disrupting
the electron transport
chain where now
the aerobic is shifting
to the anaerobic.
So that loss of
oxygen is going to
cause the patient
to appear very pink.
And usually the way
that's managed is by
giving hydroxycobalamin,
which is B12.
So hydroxycobalamin
in the presence
of cyanide makes
cyanocobalamin.
Whatever you don't
use as a B vitamin
can be excreted
because, remember,
B vitamins are
water-soluble.
So B is the correct
answer. Digoxin is
going to be not only
a positive inotropic,
it's going to be
negative coronotropic.
And it's considered
to be, in
fact, an AV node
suppressant.
Okay, and remember
with digoxin, not
only are we very careful
with electrolytes,
we know that
when the patient
presents with a
change in their vision
where they're seeing
yellow and green
halos over objects,
that might be toxicity.
You may want to
draw a dig level.
And that has to do
with the fact that
those sodium
potassium ATPase here
is going to be
blocked in the retina.
The other thing
is that digoxin,
as its backbone,
looks estrogenic.
So that's another
drug that can
create an increase
in the chest mass.
And then there's certain
drug interactions.
Anticids may
decrease absorption.
as will bile acid
resins, and so they
need to be spaced
apart from the DIG.
And then amiodarone
can raise DIG
levels by SIP
inhibition. And then I
also mentioned
that rapamil and
quinidine, which
are antiarrhythmics,
may decrease digoxin's
elimination because
they can, in fact,
block P-glycoproteins.
So that's it for
now. I will say that
if you have any
questions, I will be
available by email
or if you want a
short meeting. So
please let me know.
And until then,
have a great
day and I will
see you soon.